Guide to the Papers of Cecilia Razovsky (1886-1968), undated, 1913-1971
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, N.Y.
- Series VIII: United Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society Service, undated, 1955, 1957-1958, 1964-1965; Box 7, Folders 1-19, and Oversized Folder.
  - Subseries 1: Brazil, undated, 1955, 1957-1959, 1964-1965; Box 7, Folders 1-7.
    - UHS Representative - Brazil, undated, 1957, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Tables of statistics, unknown author., October 28, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Statistics for the number and nationality of immigrants arriving at unknown country (presumably Brazil, unknown city) from January 1st to September 30th, 1957, and the cost of medical assistance and relief.
      - Tables of statistics, unknown author., November 1, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Number and nationality of refugees arriving in São Paulo during October 1957.
      - Report, unknown author (presumably Razovsky). "Report on My Visit to New York Organizations.", November 1, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        The author visited and summarizes the activites of the United HIAS Service, NCJW, New York Association for New Americans, and the Jewish Social Service Bureau of Paterson, New Jersey.
      - Schedule of Activities, by Razovsky., November 12-13, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        For "week 3". Summarizes Razovsky's office work and meeting attendance.
      - Memorandum from Razovsky to Florence Jacobson., August 27, 1957 and November 13, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Razovsky informs Jacobson of the name of a medicine she used. Attached is correspondence between I. Dijour, United HIAS Service, New York, to Razovsky. I. Dijour is looking for a survivor. Razovsky discovers the person perished in a concentration camp. I. Dijour writes, "I admire your maybe old-fashioned, but human approach to your new duties in a somewhat unusual environment..."
      - Minutes, INIC (National Institute of Immigration and Colonization)., November 14, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Report No. 4, by Arthur Gottesman. "Porto Alegre Office.", November 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Razovsky visited the office and organized a ladies group.
      - Copy of letter, from Roberto Levy, Presidente da Loja Nachman Bialik, Belo Horizonte, Brazil to Federacao das Sociedades Israelitas Brasileiras do Estado de São Paulo., November 18 and 21, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Attached is a copy of a letter from Jojchen Orenstein, São Paulo to Roberto Levy, Presidente da Loja Nachman Bialik. A third letter from Jojchen Orenstein to Levy is dated November 21, 1957.
      - Handwritten notes, by Razovsky., December 3, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Concerning a Conselho meeting.
      - Table of Statistics, São Paulo., December 3, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Arrivals and assistance given to Jewish refugees from January 1 to October 31, 1957. By month, number of cases, and number of persons.
      - Report, by Razovsky. "Visit to Porto Alegre.", December 6, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        (See Item #36.) Her visit included a meeting with the Centisra Committee that agreed to take care of 50 families, funding to be raised to assist the families, the necessity of organizing women committees to assist the families with finding apartments, doctors visits, etc.
      - Copy of letter from Rabbi Pinkuss to Mr. Jacobson, United HIAS Service, São Paulo, Brazil., December 9, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Rabbi Pinkuss provides a rabbinical ruling that mixed marriages, Jewish and non-Jewish, must receive regular and complete assistance, "as if both were jewish. The reason ist [sic] that the non-jewish partner gave proof of his loyalty by the mere fact of making the sacrifice of emigration with the jewish partner..."
      - Notice., December 9, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Lists items of priority. Back of notice has handwritten notes by Razovsky.
      - Copy of letter from F. Kaiser, Secretary, Sociedad de Beneficencia Israelita de 1870, Lima, Peru to Mr. Jacobson, United HIAS Service, Rio de Janiero, Brazil., December 12, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Kaiser appeals to Jacobson to respond to the Sociedad's previous requests.
      - Copy of letter from Israel G. Jacobson, Director, United HIAS Service, Brazil to F. Kaiser, Secretary, Sociedad de Beneficencia Israelita de 1870., December 12, 1957; 2 copies. (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Jacobson has recently returned from New York, and will arrange a meeting with Kaiser in the next few weeks.
      - Copy of memorandum from Beno Klein to Israel G. Jacobson. "Field Trip to Belo Horizonte, December 13-17, 1957., December 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Belo Horizonte still seems promising in regards to settling refugees.
      - Draft of report, unknown author., undated; Page 2 and 3. (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Perhaps a continuation of Item #44.
      - Draft of report, unknown author., December 14, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Report concerns the "positive immigration policy" in Brazil. The report describes the INIC (National Institute of Immigration and Colonization).
      - Table of statistics. "Total of Cases, Adults and Children in Our Active Case-Load: Europeans, North Africans, and Others.", December 19, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Copy of letter from Arthur Kleinman to Israel Jacobson, Rio de Janeiro., December 27, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Kleinman encloses tables of statistics summarizing refugee relief payments provided by the Conselho. The figures are listed by nationality, and include Israeli born arrivals.
      - Copy of letter from Beno Klein, United HIAS Service, Latin American Headquarters, to Roberto Levy, Belo Horizonte., December 31, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Copy of telegram from F. Kaiser, Sociedad de Beneficiencia Israelita de 1870, to Jacobson., December 30, 1957 and January 2, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Kaiser has made hotel reservations for Razovsky. Attached is a copy of a telegram from Jacobson to F. Kaiser, informing Kaiser that Razovsky will be visiting Lima to assist with any problems. Attached are letters between F. Kaiser and United HIAS Service, Rio de Janeiro, requesting response to Kaiser's previous letters to the United HIAS Service (See Item #45 and Item #46).
      - Draft of report, unknown author (presumably Razovsky). "Report on Belo Horizonte.", January 13, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Copy of memorandum from Razovsky to Israel Jacobson and Beno Klein., January 8, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        She and Dr. Davidson are in Belo Horizonte and she summarizes the individuals she met with this week and her expectations for work the coming week.
      - Copy of memorandum from Jack Risk to Israel G. Jacobson., December 30, 1957 and January 10, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Dr. Moises Kahn was just elected President of the Federation. Risk met with Kahn, who sharply criticized the work of the Federation, the Conselho, the United HIAS Service, and other organizations. Attached to the letter is a list of officers for the Federacao das Sociedades Israelitas Brasileriras do Estado de São Paulo.
      - Incomplete copy of a report., undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Report begins on page 37, with "Argentina." After a general summary of the political and economical situation, the report details immigration in Argentina. The report then summarizes the situation in Ecuador.
      - Letter from the Davidsons to an unknown "National News Letter." "Attitudes of Brasilians Regarding Immigration.", undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Razovsky responds to an article in the December issue of the newsletter titled "Immigration to Brasil."
      - Report, by unknown author (presumably Razovsky). "Profile of São Paulo.", undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - List of contacts, Brazil., undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Copy of letter, unknown author to "Distinguidas Amigas.", undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - UHS Representative - Brazil Activity Reports, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Activities Report, by Razovsky., May 1957 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        The Davidsons arrived in São Paulo on May 7 and found the United HIAS Service office well-organized and efficient. More staff was needed to carry the heavy work load. Razovsky details her impressions and recommendations of the offices of United HIAS and Conselho de Assistencia Social.
      - Activities Report No. 34, by Razovsky., July 31, 1957; 2 copies. (Box 7, Folder 3)
        The report includes tables of statistics from January 1 to July 31, 1957 for Arrivals to Rio de Janeiro and São Paulo; a table listing the assistance given to refugees through committees for January 1 to July 31, 1957; and a summary of job application and placements. A detailed activity report covering all areas is attached.
      - Activities Report No. 35, by Razovsky., August 1957 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        The report includes tables of statistics from January 1 to August 31, 1957 for Arrivals to Rio de Janeiro and São Paulo; a table listing the assistance given to refugees through committees for January 1 to August 31, 1957; and a summary of job application and placements. A detailed activity report covering all areas is attached.
      - Activities Report No. 36, by Razovsky., September 1957 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        The report includes tables of statistics from January 1 to September 31, 1957 for Arrivals to Rio de Janeiro and São Paulo; a table listing the assistance given to refugees through committees for January 1 to September 31, 1957; a summary of job application and placements, and the number of school age children by nationality. A detailed activity report covering all areas is attached.
      - Activities Report No. 37, by Razovsky., October 1957 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        The report includes tables of statistics from January 1 to October 31, 1957 for Arrivals to Rio de Janeiro and São Paulo; a table listing the assistance given to refugees through committees for January 1 to October 31, 1957; a table entitled "Family Composition," and a table listing persons considered for resettlement in Porto Alegre and in Curitiba. A detailed activity report covering all areas is attached.
      - Activities Report No. 38, by Razovsky, November 1957., November-December 1957 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        The report includes tables of statistics from January 1 to November 30, 1957 for Arrivals to Rio de Janeiro and São Paulo; a table listing the assistance given to refugees through committees for January 1 to November 30, 1957; a table entitled "Family Composition," and a summary of job application and placements. A detailed activity report covering all areas is attached. (2 copies) The report includes a letter from Elisa M. Abramovich, Organisacao Feminina, Israelita de Assistencia Social, São Paulo to Razovsky, December 6, 1957. Abromovich describes the courses and number of Egyptian students enrolled in language and preparatory classes for secondary school. (2 copies). Also included is a letter from Rabbi Pinkus to the United HIAS Service in São Paulo, December 9, 1957. The Rabbi gives a ruling that non-Jewish partners and children from non-Jewish and Jewish mixed marriages be given complete and regular assistance, and be treated as if they were Jewish. (2 copies)
    - Egyptian Jewish Refugees in Brazil, undated, 1957, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Table of Statistics., July 23, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        Lists names of Egyptian Refugees, occupation, and number of family members.
      - Memorandum from Razovsky to Moishe Friedler., August 8, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        Razovsky attaches a statement prepared by Jacobson and Kleinbaum for the press. The statement was in response to criticism in the press against the AJDC, ICA, and indirectly the United HIAS Service.
      - Copy of memorandum from Deborah Levy, United HIAS Service, Rio de Janeiro to Arthur Gottesman, United HIAS Service, Porto Alegre., November 11, 1957; 2 copies. (Box 7, Folder 4)
        Attached is a letter enclosing the memorandum. The memorandum lists questions for a progress report on how United HIAS assisted Egyptian refugees with resettlement in local communities.
      - Copy of report, by Razovsky. "Progress Report on Egyptian Refugees in South America; From April 1, 1957 through October 31, 1957 .", November 12, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        (See Item #3.)
      - Copy of refugee profiles. Egyptian refugees., December 12, 1957; 4 pages (with 3 pages duplicated). (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Handwritten notes, by Razovsky., 1957 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        Notes on the financial conditions of various refugee families. (See Item in Oversized Folder.)
      - Tables of statistics, by Razovsky., 1957; 18 pages. (Box 7, Folder 4)
        Tables lists Brazilian refugees, age, family members, occupation, and additional observations. (See Item in Oversized Folder)
      - News article, The New York Times., October 20, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        "Egyptian Jews Getting Welcome and New Opportunities in Brazil; Migrants Admitted after Suez Crisis are Becoming Success Stories - One Heads Nation's Largest Glass Factory."
      - Copy of curriculum vitae, Hungarian refugee., undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Handwritten notes, by Razovsky., undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
        Notes regard Egyptian refugees, problems faced since 1933. Back of note reads "I've gone for milk if Mrs. Goodfriend phones please tell her I'll call her back."
    - "Forty-thousand New Brazilians", undated, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Manuscript draft, undated. "Forty Thousand New Brazilians.", undated, October 20, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 5)
        Attached is a copy of a summary of a report by NCJW, New York, titled "Developments in South America as reported by Susanna Frank in her Field Trip." The summary is dated October 20, 1964. Frank visited Bolivia (La Paz, Cochabama), Ecuador (Quito), Peru (Lima), Chile (Santiago), and Colombia (Bogota).
      - Copy of report, Susanna Frank., September 14, 1964 and December 23, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 5)
        Frank visited Bogota, Colombia and Quito, Ecuador.
      - Typed diary, by Razovsky., undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
        Incomplete journal entries recording the Davidsons visit to Mexico, Peru (Lima), and Argentina. In May, [1963].
    - Hungarian Jewish Refugees in Brazil., 1957, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Table of Statistics., July 23, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 6)
        Table lists individual refugees from Hungary, numbers of family members, dated arrived, occupation in Hungary and Brazil, salary, and observations.
      - R.E.M.P. Bulletin, Research Group for European Migration Problems, January/March 1958, Vol. 6, No. 1., January and March 1958 (Box 7, Folder 6)
        Contents: "The Role of the Intergovernmental Committee for European Migration in the Resettlement of Hungarian Refugees, 1956-1957 ," by Jules Witcover.
    - Miscellaneous., undated, 1957-1958, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Report, unknown author., July 22, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Handwritten and typed notes., circa December 20, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Maybe notes for a speech; statistics on United HIAS Service and general emigration.
      - Telegram, from United HIAS to Lima, Peru., January 28, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Regarding a refugee family and requesting money for a visa.
      - Telegram, from Davidsons in Colombia to United HIAS, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil., February 13, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Telegram concerns various matters.
      - Telegram, from Davidsons in Colombia to United HIAS, Quito, Ecuador., February 16, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 7)
        The Davidsons will be leaving Bogota for Lima and would like to arrange a meeting.
      - Telegram, from Davidsons in Colombia to United HIAS, Quito, Ecuador., undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Statistics Summary. "United HIAS Service, Summary Statistics on UHS-Assisted Migration for March and Cumulative First Quarter 1958 ." By country., April 18, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Statement draft, presumably by Razovsky., undated, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Page 4. Statement describes how German refugee doctors were allowed to study for a United States Medical License through funding by the United Jewish Appeal. Attached is a note on the Immigration Law in U.S.A., 1965, that states family reunion is easier, eliminated national origins plan, and allows for professional or needed workers to be given preference for admission.
      - Report, unknown author. "Report on Refugee Problems.", undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Report stresses the need for a system to track aliens and the activities of refugee relief organizations. The report recommends appointing the Red Cross as the supervising agency, and replacing the President's Advisory Committee with a new Advisory Committee on Refugee Problems with the Red Cross Vice-President as Chairman.
      - Report, unknown author. "Comment on Report on Refugee Problems.", undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
        The comments point out assumptions made by the Report on Refugee Problems and states "Under these circumstances the proposal that the American Red Cross undertake supervision and checking of aliens seems impractical..."
      - Speech address, by Razovsky. "Twentienth Century Migration with Special Reference to Jews." An address delivered for the United Jewish Appeal that talks of Razovsky's observations in Latin America and particularly Brazil., undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Report, incomplete., undated; Pages 2 and 3. (Box 7, Folder 7)
        The report corrects misconceptions concerning Brazil economic, geographic, and social situations.
      - Report, incomplete., undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Page 3. Razovsky relates an anecdote about a refugee who told her that the AJDC Paris office "did things differently" as far as handling immigrant cases.
      - Copy of report, incomplete., undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Page 3. Subtitled "'Rescue' Immigration." Brazilian procedures for issuing visas to Egyptian refugees.
      - Copy of report, incomplete., undated; One page. (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Signed by the Asociacion de Sociedades Israelitas and United HIAS Service.
      - Copy of a form letter, Comite de Auxilio Aos Imigrantes., undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Copy of an outline. "Division of Immigration and International Service.", undated; One page, may be incomplete. (Box 7, Folder 7)
        The outline provides a tentative organization plan for the Division.
      - Copy of a report, incomplete. Subtitled "Examples in Which Assistance Could Be Extended Immediately if Funds Were Forthcoming.", undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Lists individual refugees (mostly German) now living in France, and their particular needs.
      - Letter, incomplete, from Razovsky to friends., August 7, no year; Page 2. (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Razovsky describes Hungarian and Egyptian refugees newly arrived in Brazil.
      - Copy of report, incomplete. "Conclusions About Latin America and the West Coast.", undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
        General, one or two sentence statements on the immigration possibilities in various Latin American countries.
      - Report, incomplete, by Razovsky. "Antisemitism in South America.", undated; 2 pages. (Box 7, Folder 7)
        First page is a general historical background of anti-Semitism in the Catholic Church and its influence in South America. The second page concerns Brazil. The anti-Semitism is linked to the Integralist Movement.
      - Address, unknown author., undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Introduces Razovsky as a speaker and a new representative for the United HIAS Service. For a presentation given in São Paulo, Brazil to the Conselho.
      - Manuscript draft, by Razovsky. "A Quarter Century of Brazil's Progress.", undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
        Attached are handwritten notes.
  - Subseries 2: South America, undated, 1939, 1955, 1957-1959; Box 7, Folders 8-19.
    Folders are arranged by subject and country.
    This subseries contains reports, correspondence, memorandum, article, telegrams, daily logs, contact lists, and refugee case lists. The subseries includes Box 7, Folders 8-19.
    Box 7, Folder 8 primarily relates to Razovsky's acceptance and the employment conditions of her new position as South American Resettlement Supervisor. A letter dated December 12, 1957 mentions the Davidsons' adopted daughter, who lives in La Paz, Bolivia and outlines the Davidsons' itinerary as they update countries' profiles.
    Box 7, Folder 9 includes general correspondence pertaining to travel arrangements, and updates on Razovsky's visits to various South American countries. A memorandum dated April 23, 1958 by Razovsky recommends that overseas staff be completely oriented to the culture of a refugee's country of origin, and that refugees be informed of the positive and negative aspects of their new homes. A report by Israel Jacobson, circa 1958, describes United HIAS Service activities in Uruguay, Venezuela, Colombia, Peru, Bolivia, Paraguay, Cuba, Panama, and other South American countries. An article from American Judaism, dated January 1959, is titled "They do Well in South America." Correspondence between Razovsky, Edward Marks (Executive Director of the U.S. Committee for Refugees), and Al Goldstein (Director, Jewish Community Council, Houston, Texas), discuss the "difficult time" Hungarian refugees are having in Texas.
    Box 7, Folders 10-19 are titled accordingly by country, and contain material regarding the Davidsons' organization activities and research in preparation of each countries' profile. Drafts and final versions of the Davidsons' and other authors' reports are enclosed. Extensive documentation is available on the Davidsons' visits to Chile, Colombia, Mexico, and Peru. Less documented are the Davidsons' visits to Ecuador, Panama and Paraguay. The sole items in the folders for Panama, Bolivia, Costa Rica and Guatemala, and Venezuela are reports by other authors.
    See also: Series I: Personal, Subseries 2: Personal Documents and Correspondence; Series I: Personal, Subseries 4: Later Years; Series III: NCC; Series IV: NRS; and Series V: AJDC/UNRRA.
    - United HIAS Service - South American Resettlement Supervisor, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Letter from James Rice, Acting Executive Director, United HIAS Service, New York to Razovsky, Austin, Texas., March 26, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 8)
        Rice confirms her assignment with the United HIAS Service in Brazil.
      - Copy of letter from Razovsky, Austin, Texas to James Rice, United HIAS Service, New York., March 30, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 8)
        She accepts the employment conditions and asks for transportation arrangements to be made to Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.
      - Copy of letter from Razovsky, Austin, Texas to James Rice., April 4 and 7, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 8)
        She would like to ship their car to Brazil. She is studying the reports he sent her, and "are eager to get to work." Attached is a letter from Rice to Razovsky. He encloses addresses of the Brazilian United HIAS Service offices.
      - Copy of form., April 18, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 8)
        Information requested for an application form.
      - Letter from James Rice to Razovsky., April 19, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 8)
        Confirmation of her assignment as a Resettlement Supervisor to the Brazilian Operations of the United HIAS Service. She will report to Israel G. Jacobson, Director of Latin American operations.
      - Copy of letter from Dr. Morris Davidson, Austin, Texas to Brazilian Consul, Houston, TX., April 20, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 8)
        He is applying for a tourist visa to Brazil, and includes requested documents (not attached in folder).
      - Letter from James Rice to Razovsky., May 1, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 8)